Guide to the Howell Wright Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Howell Wright collection
1868-1977
MS 565
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
18.75
The collection consists of correspondence, photographs, clippings, and printed material relating to the history of Rhodesia and South Africa, with specific focus on Jameson's Raid, 1895-1896, the Johannesburg Reform Committee, and Cecil John Rhodes. Correspondence includes letters with numerous individuals active in the government and military forces in South Africa and Rhodesia, and with friends, relatives, and associates of those individuals. These letters were solicited by Wright and contain the reminiscences of and comments about such figures as: Frederick Russell Burnham, Jack Carruthers, Louis Cohen, John Hays Hammond, J. B. M. Hertzog, Sir Leander Starr Jameson, Cecil Rhodes, George Bernard Shaw, and Jan Christian Smuts.
Wright, Howell, 1882-1954
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to Yale University by Howell Wright, 1941. Transferred from the African Curator, 2005. Gift of Bradford Wright, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and five additions: I. Correspondence, 1886-1954. II. Photographs, 1890-1902. III. Printed Material, 1900-1950. IV. Personal Papers, 1910-1953.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, photographs, clippings, and printed material relating to the history of Rhodesia and South Africa, with specific focus on Jameson's Raid, 1895-1896, the Johannesburg Reform Committee, and Cecil John Rhodes.
Correspondence includes letters with numerous individuals active in the government and military forces in South Africa and Rhodesia, and with friends, relatives, and associates of those individuals. These letters were solicited by Wright and contain the reminiscences of and comments about such figures as: Frederick R. Burnham, Jack Carruthers, Louis Cohen, John Hays Hammond, J. B. M. Hertzog, Sir Leander Starr Jameson, Cecil Rhodes, George Bernhard Shaw, and Jan Christian Smuts.
The Howell Wright Collection is arranged in four series:
I. Correspondence, 1886-1954
II. Photographs, 1890-1902
III. Printed Material, 1900-1950
IV. Personal Papers, 1910-1953
Series I, Correspondence, contains the letters and other materials solicited by Howell Wright to document the history South Africa and Rhodesia, with a particular emphasis on the role of the British government and military forces in the late nineteenth century. Wright corresponded with many figures who held governmental and military positions in the region, and with relatives and associates of these individuals. These correspondents include men who served in the Pioneer Corps, and who were involved in the Bachuanaland Expedition, 1884-1888; Jameson's Raid, 1895-1896, and the Johannesburg Reform Committee.
Many correspondents, including Jack Carruthers, Charles Llewellyn Anderson, James Donaldson, and Sir Frederick Hamilton, provided lengthy personal reminiscences of their lives and experiences in South Africa. A variety of printed material, photographs, and newspaper clippings, often enclosed with these letters, adds another dimension to the lives of these people.
Series II, Photographs, 1892-1990, is arranged in two sections: Rhodes, Cecil John; and South Africa. Rhodes, Cecil John, contains two hundred and ninety (290) photographs of Cecil John Rhodes and the South African region. They are reproductions of items located in the Central African Archives.
The South Africa section contains photograph albums relating to such events as the South Africa War, 1899-1902, and the Tercentenary celebration of 1952.
Series III, Printed Material, ca. 1900-1950, contains a variety of publications collected by Howell Wright. Items include journals and journal articles relating to the history of South Africa and Rhodesia and publications written by Wright on topics such as municipal government and city policies.
Series IV, Personal Papers, 1910-1953, contains books, clippings, printed material, and miscellanea relating to Howell Wright, his family, the development of his collection of manuscripts and materials relating to South Africa and Rhodesia, and miscellanea.
Oversize consists of large printed material, documents, and items (including photostats) collected by Wright on individuals and organizations active in South Africa and Rhodesia.
Biographical / Historical
Howell Wright was born in Swansea, Massachusetts, on January 21, 1882. He graduated from Yale University (B.A., 1906) and served as a municipal official in Cleveland, Ohio, for several years. He collected books, manuscripts, and photographs on Rhodesia and South Africa until his death in 1954.
Jameson's Raid, 1895-1896; South African War, 1899-1902; Africa; Rhodesia and Nyasaland; South Africa -- History -- 1836-1909; South Africa -- Politics and government -- 1836-1909; Transvaal (South Africa); Zimbabwe; Photographs; Lobengula, King of the Matabele, approximately 1833-1893?; Allen, Carleton Kemp, 1887-1966; Baden-Powell of Gilwell, Robert Stephenson Smyth Baden-Powell, Baron, 1857-1941; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937; Beard, Charles A. (Charles Austin), 1874-1948; Beit, Alfred, 1853-1906; Bower, Graham, 1848-1933; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922; Burnham, Frederick Russell, 1861-1947; Carruthers, Jack; Chamberlain, Joseph, 1836-1914; Clements, P.B.; Cohen, Louis, 1854-; Colquhoun, Ethel Maud Cookson; Cooper-Chadwick, J., 1864-; Cornwall, William L.; Curzon of Kedleston, George Nathaniel Curzon, Marquess, 1859-1925; Davis, Richard Harding, 1864-1916; DuToit, Martin Andrʹe; Fraser, John George, Sir, 1840-1927; Goldman, Charles Sydney, 1868-; Hammond, John Hays, 1855-1936; Hertzog, James Barry Munnik, 1866-1942; Heymans, Guillaume; Jameson, L. S. (Leander Starr), 1853-1917; Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936; Kotzé, J. G. (John Gilbert), 1849-1940; Lothian, Philip Henry Kerr, Marquis of, 1882-1940; Moffat, Harold Unwin, 1869-; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Radziwill, Catherine, Princess, 1858-1941; Rhodes, Cecil, 1853-1902; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Rose-Innes, J. (James), 1855-1942; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950; Sibbett, Cecil John, 1881-; Smuts, Jan Christiaan, 1870-1950; Tabler, Edward C.; Thompson, Matabele, 1857-1927; Tredgold, Robert, Sir, 1899-1977; Wright, Howell, 1882-1954; Johannesburg Reform Committee
- Correspondence, 1886-1954; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged alphabetically by the individual and/or organization.
  - Adams, H. J., 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adcook, Roger W., 1890-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
  - Albu, Sir George W., 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Allen, C. K., 1936-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arnold, Howard A., 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Authors Club, 1931-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Aydelotte, Frank, 1938-1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baden-Powell, Sir Robert, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Baker, Herbert, 1935-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Baker, Newton D., 1922-1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bailey, R. E. H., undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Barnato, (Mrs.) Barney, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Barter, Evelina, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Beard, Charles, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Beit, Sir Alfred, 1937-1946 (Box 1, Folder 15A)
  - Benedetto, Georgette Labram, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Berthoud, Ferdinand, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Black, Annie, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Boggie, Jeannie M., 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Boonzaier, Daniel Cornelius, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Botha, Colin Graham, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Botha, Philip Rudolph, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bowen, George J., 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bower, Sir Graham, 1905-1946 (Box 2, Folder 24 - 26)
  - Bower, Lady Graham, 1933-1937 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Bradley, R., 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Bradley, C. K., 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Branch, George T., 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Bredell, H. C., 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Bridges, Sir Tom, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - British South Africa Company, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Brown, William Harvey, 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Browne, W. H., 1951 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Bryce, James Bryce, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Bryden, Olivia, 1940-1947 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Bryden, R. A., 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Buchan, John (Lord Tweedsmuir), 1936 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Bulawayo Chronicle, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Burnham, Frederick Russell, 1908-1951, n.d (Box 2, Folder 41 - 42)
  - Culpin, George Harold, 1941-1950 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Camp, R. C., 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Campbell, Killie, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Candler, G. C., 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Cape Times, 1936-1939 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Carnegie, William Arnold, 1907-1953 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Carruthers, Jack, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 49 - 52)
  - Chadwick, J. Copper, 1929-1948 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Chamberlain, Joseph, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Chamberlain, Neville, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Chennels, (Mrs.) W. R., 1938 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Chilvers, Hedley A., 1930-1940 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Christiansen, Maja (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Churchill, Winston, 1939-1943 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Clements, P. B., 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Cleveland, Milton Evan, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Clinton, William J., 1938 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Cloete, Stuart, 1938-1946 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Close, Ralph U., 1937-1942 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Cohen, Louis
    - "Kimberly in the Seventies" (Box 5, Folder 65 - 70)
    - "A Romance of the Rend" (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - "Reminiscence of Johannesburg..." (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Notes and Miscellanea (Box 6, Folder 73 - 74)
    - Scrapbooks (Box 7, Folder 75 - 79)
  - Collins-Gurr, William, 1949-1953 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Colenbrander, (Mrs.) J. W., 1938-1939 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Colville, Bertram, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Colvin, Ian Duncan, 1936-1938 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Consolidated Goldfields of South Africa, 1937-1948 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Cooper, Henry W. A., undated (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Cornwall, William Lundie, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Corryndon, Sir Robert, undated (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Crawford, John L., 1938-1951 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Creighton, C. F., 1938-1944 (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Cripps, Lionel, 1929-1939 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Currey, Ronald, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Curtis, Lionel, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Curzan, George Nathaniel, Curzan, 1st Marquis (1859-1925), 1909 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Darter, Adrian, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Davis, John, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - Davis, Lady Mary, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Davis, Richard Harding, 1902 (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - d'Erlanger, Baron Emile B., 1939 (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Dewet, Johannes J., 1938 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Diamond Fields Advisor, 1937-1938 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Divine, Charles H., 1937-1951 (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - Dollar, Duncan, 1937 (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - Douglas-Jones, Lady, 1937 (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - Drew, (Mrs.) Alfred, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - Duncan, Graham, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 105)
  - Du Rout, J., 1937 (Box 9, Folder 106)
  - Duckworth-Ford, R. A., 1947 (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - Dutoit, C. M., 1937 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - Edmonds, J. A., 1936-1941 (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - Edwards, Sam, 1938-1939 (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - Eliot, A. E. A., 1937-1942 (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Eliott, Leslie, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Elton, Geoffrey Elton, 1946-1947 (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Emden, Paul H., 1936-1939 (Box 9, Folder 114)
  - Everett, Frite, 1937-1938 (Box 9, Folder 115)
  - Eyre, Mary, 1938-1939 (Box 9, Folder 116)
  - Fairbridge, W. E., 1938-1945 (Box 9, Folder 117)
  - Ferreira, H. M., 1938-1939 (Box 9, Folder 118)
  - Fort, Seymour, 1937-1944 (Box 9, Folder 119)
  - Fraser, Sir John George, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 120)
  - Fry, Ivan, 1937-1938 (Box 9, Folder 121)
  - Gale, W. D., 1937-1938 (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - Garlick, B. R., 1937-1938 (Box 10, Folder 123)
  - Gavin, James L., 1936-1939 (Box 10, Folder 124)
  - Gascoigne, F. R. R. T., undated (Box 10, Folder 125)
  - Gibson, George Fleming, 1937-1939 (Box 10, Folder 126)
  - Gies, Albert, 1937, 1949-1953 (Box 10, Folder 127)
  - Goldman, Charles Sidney, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 128)
  - Grant, Henry, undated (Box 10, Folder 129)
  - Grauman, Sir Harry, 1936-1937 (Box 10, Folder 130)
  - Gray, H. Willoughby, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 131)
  - Gary, J. A., 1936-1950 (Box 10, Folder 132)
  - Green, George A. L., 1935-1953 (Box 10, Folder 133)
  - Green, James, 1903 (Box 10, Folder 134)
  - Green, William, 1925 (Box 10, Folder 135)
  - Grimmer, W. P., 1938-1939 (Box 10, Folder 136)
  - Grissaer, Sister Anna, 1931-1943 (Box 10, Folder 137 - 138)
  - Grobler, Piet, 1937-1938 (Box 10, Folder 139)
  - Halifax, Edward, Frederick Undley Wood, 3rd Viscount, 1944-1945 (Box 11, Folder 140)
  - Hall, James Norman, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 141)
  - Hamilton, Sir Frederick, 1936-1942 (Box 11, Folder 142 - 143)
  - Hammond, John Hays, 1895, 1934-1944 (Box 11, Folder 144)
  - Hammond, (Mrs.) John Hays, 1901 (Box 11, Folder 145)
  - Hammond, John Hays, Jr., 1936-1938 (Box 11, Folder 146)
  - Harding, Colin, 1937-1938 (Box 11, Folder 147)
  - Harger, Harold Scott, 1938-1939 (Box 11, Folder 148)
  - Harraway, H. G., 1938 (Box 11, Folder 149)
  - Harris, David, 1936-1938 (Box 11, Folder 150)
  - Harris, Frederick Rutherford, 1937-1938 (Box 11, Folder 151)
  - Hay, A. G., 1937 (Box 11, Folder 152)
  - Henderson, H. S., 1943 (Box 11, Folder 153)
  - Harry, Maurice, 1937-1940 (Box 11, Folder 154)
  - Hertzog, James Barry Munnik, undated (Box 11, Folder 155)
  - Heyman, Melville, 1937-1938 (Box 11, Folder 156)
  - Heymans, Guillaume, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 157)
  - Heys, George J., 1943 (Box 11, Folder 158)
  - Hirschorn, Frederick, 1937-1941 (Box 11, Folder 159)
  - Hofmeyr, Jan H., 1935-1939 (Box 12, Folder 160)
  - Hole, Hugh Marshall, 1929, 1935-1948 (Box 12, Folder 161)
  - Honey, W. S., 1936 (Box 12, Folder 162)
  - Hoste, H. F., 1938 (Box 12, Folder 163)
  - Household, Goodman, undated (Box 12, Folder 164)
  - Howard, Walter, 1937-1938 (Box 12, Folder 165)
  - Higgins, Godfrey Martin, 1937, 1943 (Box 12, Folder 166)
  - Humes, A. W., 1951 (Box 12, Folder 167)
  - Immelman, R. F., 1938-1940 (Box 12, Folder 168)
  - Inskipp, Percy S., 1929-1939 (Box 12, Folder 169)
  - Jacobz, S. C., 1938-1940 (Box 12, Folder 170)
  - Jameson, James, 1951 (Box 12, Folder 171)
  - Jameson, Leander Starr and Robert W., 1892-1940 (Box 12, Folder 172)
  - Jameson's Raid, 1895-1896
    - Barry, John William, 1938, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 173)
    - Bodle, William, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 174)
    - Bowden, Frank L., 1938 (Box 13, Folder 175)
    - Cashel, Rowan, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 176)
    - Cazalet, A., 1938 (Box 13, Folder 177)
    - Chawner, H. W., 1938 (Box 13, Folder 178)
    - Chawaorth-Masters, A. H., 1938 (Box 13, Folder 179)
    - Constable, Harry, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 180)
    - Coventry, Charles, J., 1938 (Box 13, Folder 181)
    - Drury, Gordon Vallancy, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 182)
    - Dykes, L. L. Ballantyne, 1937-1939 (Box 13, Folder 183)
    - Farmer, W., 1938 (Box 13, Folder 184)
    - Fletcher, H. C., 1946 (Box 13, Folder 185)
    - Foley, Cyril, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 186)
    - Garraway, Edward C. F., 1938-1940 (Box 13, Folder 187)
    - Gosling, Audley Vaughan, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 188)
    - Grenfell, Harold M., 1940 (Box 13, Folder 189)
    - Grey, Raleigh, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 190)
    - Heany, Maurice, 1938-1942 (Box 13, Folder 191)
    - Holden, Edward Charles, 1916 (Box 13, Folder 192)
    - Hore, A. H. J., 1937-1938 (Box 13, Folder 193)
    - Jameson, Leander Starr, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 194)
    - Jesser-Coope, J. C., 1937 (Box 13, Folder 195)
    - Kennedy, James Hutchinson, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 196)
    - Kincaid-Smith, K. J., 1935-1936 (Box 13, Folder 197)
    - Lakie, W., 1938 (Box 13, Folder 198)
    - Lindsell, Charles F., 1896 (Box 13, Folder 199)
    - McQueen, James, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 200)
    - Munro, C. L. D., 1937-1938, 1944-1945 (Box 13, Folder 201)
    - Murray, William H. E., 1940 (Box 13, Folder 202)
    - Raiders, list of, undated (Box 13, Folder 203)
    - Scott, Harry J., 1938 (Box 13, Folder 204)
    - Spain, W. S., 1938-1942 (Box 13, Folder 205)
    - Stacy-Clitherow, John Bourchier, 1937-1938 (Box 13, Folder 206)
    - Straker, Martin, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 207)
    - Tomlinson, Alfred Jones, 1937-1939 (Box 13, Folder 208)
    - Villiers, Charles Hyde, undated (Box 13, Folder 209)
    - White, Henry Frederick, undated (Box 13, Folder 210)
    - White, Robert, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 211)
    - Williams, G. H. P., 1936 (Box 13, Folder 212)
    - Willoughby, John C., 1899, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 213)
    - Wood, Edward A., 1938 (Box 13, Folder 214)
  - Jarvis, Weston, 1937-1938 (Box 14, Folder 215 - 216)
  - Jennings, Hennen, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 217)
  - Johannesburg Reform Committee
    - Photographs, undated (Box 14, Folder 218)
    - Alder, Henry, undated (Box 14, Folder 219)
    - Andersson, Charles Llewellyn, 1936-1945 (Box 14, Folder 220)
    - Auvet, J. B., undated (Box 14, Folder 221)
    - Bailey, Abe, 1936-1938 (Box 14, Folder 222)
    - Bell, William Henry Somerset, 1937-1939 (Box 14, Folder 223)
    - Bettleheim, H., 1936 (Box 14, Folder 224)
    - Bettington, H., 1930-1945 (Box 14, Folder 225)
    - Brodie, William Hampden, undated (Box 14, Folder 226)
    - Brown, Alf, 1938-1939 (Box 14, Folder 227)
    - Buckland, J. M., undated (Box 14, Folder 228)
    - Butters, Charles, 1937-1938 (Box 14, Folder 229)
    - Carr, William St. John, undated (Box 14, Folder 230)
    - Clement, Victor Michael, 1937-1941 (Box 14, Folder 231)
    - Cohen, H. F., undated (Box 14, Folder 232)
    - Committee: miscellanea, 1937-1940 (Box 14, Folder 233 - 235)
    - Curtis, J. S., undated (Box 14, Folder 236)
    - Davies, William T. F., 1936-1938 (Box 14, Folder 237)
    - Davis, W. D., undated (Box 14, Folder 238)
    - Donaldson, James, 1936-1949 (Box 14, Folder 239)
    - Dubois, Philip, undated (Box 15, Folder 240)
    - Duirs, David P., 1941 (Box 15, Folder 241)
    - Dunbar, George A. D., 1937-1940 (Box 15, Folder 242)
    - Fitzpatrick, Sir Percy, 1927-1935 (Box 15, Folder 243)
    - Fricker, Robert George, undated (Box 15, Folder 244)
    - Garland, C. A., undated (Box 15, Folder 245)
    - Gifillan, Douglas Flemmer, 1937-1938 (Box 15, Folder 246)
    - Goddard, William, undated (Box 15, Folder 247)
    - Goldring, A. R., undated (Box 15, Folder 248)
    - Gray, Frederic, undated (Box 15, Folder 249)
    - Head, William Beachy, undated (Box 15, Folder 250)
    - Hillier, Alfred P., 1938 (Box 15, Folder 251)
    - Hosken, William, 1938 (Box 15, Folder 252)
    - Hudson, Walter, 1939 (Box 15, Folder 253)
    - Hull, H. C., 1938 (Box 15, Folder 254)
    - Hutchinson, E. O., undated (Box 15, Folder 255)
    - Joel, S. B., undated (Box 15, Folder 256)
    - Keenan, _______, undated (Box 15, Folder 257)
    - King, Henry James, undated (Box 15, Folder 258)
    - Lace, John, undated (Box 15, Folder 259)
    - Langerman, Max, undated (Box 15, Folder 260)
    - Lawley, Arthur L. - Leonard, James, 1938-1939 (Box 15, Folder 261)
    - Malville, Edward, H. V., undated (Box 15, Folder 262)
    - Mein, Thomas, undated (Box 15, Folder 263)
    - Mosenthal, Fritz, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 264)
    - Mullins, Charles H., undated (Box 15, Folder 265)
    - Niven, Andrew Mackie, undated (Box 15, Folder 266)
    - Pakeman, E. J., undated (Box 15, Folder 267)
    - Phillips, Lionel, 1936 (Box 15, Folder 268)
    - Rhodes, Frank, undated (Box 15, Folder 269)
    - Richards, George, undated (Box 15, Folder 270)
    - Roger, John Andrew, undated (Box 15, Folder 271)
    - Rogers, William Heyward, undated (Box 15, Folder 272)
    - Sandilands, Gordon, undated (Box 15, Folder 273)
    - Sauer, Hans, 1896, 1937-1939 (Box 15, Folder 274)
    - Solomon, Edward P., undated (Box 15, Folder 275)
    - Somershield, Oscar, undated (Box 15, Folder 276)
    - Spencer, Francis H., 1937-1943 (Box 15, Folder 277)
    - Strange, Harold Fairbrother, undated (Box 15, Folder 278)
    - Tremeer, Charles A. C., undated (Box 15, Folder 279)
    - Van Hulsteijn, Willem, 1936-1937 (Box 15, Folder 280)
    - Williams, J. L., undated (Box 15, Folder 281)
    - Witwatersrand, University of, 1937-1938 (Box 15, Folder 282)
    - Wolf, Henry A., 1936-1938 (Box 15, Folder 283)
    - Wolff, Victor, undated (Box 15, Folder 284)
    - Wooloston, H. Col., undated (Box 15, Folder 285)
    - Wools-Sampson, Aubrey, undated (Box 15, Folder 286)
  - Johnson, Frank, 1927, 1935-1941 (Box 15, Folder 287)
  - Jollie, E. Tawse, 1946 (Box 15, Folder 288)
  - Jollie, (Mrs.) E. Tawse, 1936-1939 (Box 15, Folder 289)
  - Jones, Edward, 1886, 1936 (Box 15, Folder 290)
  - Jourdan, Philip, 1902, 1937-1939, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 291)
  - Judge, J. C., 1951 (Box 15, Folder 292)
  - Jundson, Daniel, 1937-1938 (Box 15, Folder 293)
  - Juta, Marjorie, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 294)
  - Kerr, Philip Henry, 11th Marquess of Luthian, 1937-1938 (Box 16, Folder 295)
  - King Solomon's Mines, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 296)
  - Kipling, Rudyard, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 297)
  - Kotze, Sir John Gilbert, 1937-1949 (Box 16, Folder 298)
  - Krause, F. G. T., 1947-1954 (Box 16, Folder 299)
  - Krause, F. G. T., 1944, 1951-1953 (Box 16, Folder 300)
  - Krause, F. G. T.
    - Typescript, 1946, undated (Box 16, Folder 301 - 302)
    - Presidential Address, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 303)
    - Printed matter, 1946-1948, 1951 (Box 16, Folder 304)
  - Kruger, Stephanus J. P., 1889, 1895 (Box 16, Folder 305)
  - Labram, George, 1937-1940 (Box 17, Folder 306)
  - Lemperly, Paul, 1935 (Box 17, Folder 307)
  - Le Doux, S. D., 1939 (Box 17, Folder 308)
  - Leyds, Willem Johannes, 1936-1950 (Box 17, Folder 309)
  - Lewis, Noel Lawson, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 310)
  - Lilly, L. F. M., 1937-1948 (Box 17, Folder 311)
  - Little, Archibald, 1937-1938 (Box 17, Folder 312)
  - Lo Magundi Hornet, 1898 (Box 17, Folder 313)
  - London Electrotype Agency, 1937 (Box 17, Folder 314)
  - Long, Tex, 1937-1938 (Box 17, Folder 315)
  - Longden, H. W. D., 1951 (Box 17, Folder 316)
  - Low, Sir Henry T., 1947-1953 (Box 17, Folder 317)
  - Lugard, Lady Flora, 1938 (Box 17, Folder 318)
  - Lyon, Frederick, undated (Box 17, Folder 319)
  - Ludlow, Lady Alice, 1936-1938 (Box 17, Folder 320)
  - McDonald, J. G., 1936-1938 (Box 17, Folder 321)
  - McLea, John Hunter, 1937 (Box 17, Folder 322)
  - McMahon, Brien, 1950 (Box 17, Folder 323)
  - McVeau, (Mrs.) Martha W., [1953?] (Box 17, Folder 324)
  - McQueen, James, 1941 (Box 17, Folder 325)
  - Maggs, Frank B., 1937-1947 (Box 17, Folder 326)
  - Maguire, (Mrs.) James Rochefort, 1936-1938 (Box 17, Folder 327)
  - Main, Andrew Andrews, 1937-1938 (Box 17, Folder 328)
  - Malcon, James, 1937-1938 (Box 17, Folder 329)
  - Malherbe, W. S., 1937-1938 (Box 17, Folder 330)
  - Mallet Veale, A. J. and Diana, 1937-1950 (Box 17, Folder 331)
  - Maloney, Francis, 1937 (Box 17, Folder 332)
  - Mandy, G. S. T., 1937 (Box 17, Folder 333)
  - Mashonaland Herald, 1891-1892 (Box 17, Folder 334)
  - Mound, E. A., 1929 (Box 17, Folder 335)
  - May (Mrs.) J. Erskine, 1949-1954 (Box 17, Folder 336)
  - Mein, William Wallace, 1937-1938 (Box 17, Folder 337)
  - Metcalf, Theophilus J., 1936-1938 (Box 17, Folder 338)
  - Michell, Sir Lewis & Lady, 1927, 1938 (Box 17, Folder 339)
  - Millin, Sarah Gertrude, 1935-1937 (Box 18, Folder 340)
  - Moffat, Harold Unwin, 1937-1943 (Box 18, Folder 341)
  - Montague, (Mrs.) L. R., 1937-1938 (Box 18, Folder 342)
  - Morkel, Jacoba Elizabeth de la Rey, 1938-1939 (Box 18, Folder 343)
  - Murphy, Edward Stanley, 1937-1938 (Box 18, Folder 344)
  - Murray, Charles, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 345)
  - Nathan, Manfred, 1942 (Box 18, Folder 346)
  - Nesbitt, Murrogh, 1951 (Box 18, Folder 347)